<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>system-design on Umair&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://umairsaeed.com/categories/system-design/</link>
    <description>Recent content in system-design on Umair&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2023 09:45:12 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://umairsaeed.com/categories/system-design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Event Driven Architecture</title>
      <link>https://umairsaeed.com/event-driven-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2023 09:45:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://umairsaeed.com/event-driven-architecture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Event-Driven Architecture (EDA) &lt;em&gt;uses events to trigger and communicate between decoupled nodes (services)&lt;/em&gt; within the system. Producers generate initiating events (messages) when a significant change in state occurs. Components within the system subscribe to events and react to them by performing specific actions or tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Service Oriented Architecture</title>
      <link>https://umairsaeed.com/service-oriented-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2023 08:17:56 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://umairsaeed.com/service-oriented-architecture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Service-Oriented Architecture (SOA), also known as, Service-Based Architecture (SBA), is a distributed architecture pattern in which an application is organized into a collection of loosely coupled, reusable &lt;strong&gt;services&lt;/strong&gt;. Each service is a self-contained unit that performs a specific task or function, and communicates with other services using standard communication protocols, such as REST, SOAP, or gRPC.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pipeline Architecture</title>
      <link>https://umairsaeed.com/pipeline-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2023 15:59:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://umairsaeed.com/pipeline-architecture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A pipeline architecture is a monolithic architecture style, which means a single deployment unit for all of the code. The essential characteristic of pipeline architecture is that data or tasks are processed in a series of stages. Each stage receives the output from the previous stage, processes it, and passes it on to the next stage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Layered Architecture</title>
      <link>https://umairsaeed.com/layered-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 16:29:26 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://umairsaeed.com/layered-architecture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Layered Architecture is a monolithic architecture style, which means a single deployment unit for all the code. This style is also known as the &lt;em&gt;n-tiered&lt;/em&gt; architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Software Architecture Styles</title>
      <link>https://umairsaeed.com/evaluating-software-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 11:28:21 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://umairsaeed.com/evaluating-software-architecture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Software architecture is very context-dependent. Factors such as the software application&amp;rsquo;s goals, the development team&amp;rsquo;s size and budget, and business needs play a significant role in the choice of software architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
